<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A true perpetuall prognostication for the yeare 1632, being leape yeare, and for all yeares to come declaring what shall fall out in time comming, with a rule to teach every one the airt of memorie : everie yeare is like to bee leape yeare, if divers and bankerupts, may haue money on band or trust / by Allan Makcouldy ...</title>
            <author>Makcouldy, Allan.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1632</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 10 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A06766</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17206.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S1625</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">20240813</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 20240813</idno>
            <idno type="VID">23893</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A06766)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 23893)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1710:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A true perpetuall prognostication for the yeare 1632, being leape yeare, and for all yeares to come declaring what shall fall out in time comming, with a rule to teach every one the airt of memorie : everie yeare is like to bee leape yeare, if divers and bankerupts, may haue money on band or trust / by Allan Makcouldy ...</title>
                  <author>Makcouldy, Allan.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16] p. : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for my comerauds,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Dubline :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1632.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁸.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the National Library of Scotland.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Astrology --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Conduct of life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:23893:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 58 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:23893:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 58 -->
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi> TRVE PERPETVALL <hi>PROGNOSTICATION</hi> for the Yeare 1632.</p>
            <p>Being Leape yeare, and for all yeares to come. Declaring what ſhall fall out <hi>in time comming, with a rule to teach every one the airt of memorie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Everie yeare is like to bee Leape yeare, <hi>if Div<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rs and Bankcrupts, may</hi> haue money on band or truſt.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Allan Makcouldy</hi> lover of <hi>the Mathematicks.</hi>
            </p>
            <q xml:lang="lat">Tempore patet occulta veritas.</q>
            <q>In time appeareth hidden truth.</q>
            <p>DVBLINE Printed for my comerauds. 1632.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="author_to_printer">
            <pb facs="tcp:23893:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 59 -->
            <head>To the Printer.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>OOD PRINTER, I haue taken oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to ſet foorth the Treatiſe fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, vnder the title of a perpetual Prognoſtication; I haue offered the ſame to you to bee put to the Preſſe, and thereafter publiſh it to all ſuch as will deſire the ſame for money, if thy benefite bee great, it ſhall breed mee much contentment: Take paines that the faults therein bee corrected, and the ſame rightly printed: ſo ſhall you enable me to endeavour my ſelfe to put a more profitable worke in thine hands, I reſt.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Allan Makcouldy.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:23893:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 59 -->
            <head>A briefe computation of ſuch things as are paſt and what would bee prevented this yeare <hi>1632.</hi> and all yeares heere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after.</head>
            <p>EVerie one may know their owne age by the Miniſters record who baptized them, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept there bee no regiſter thereof.</p>
            <p>Howſoever everie one may know their owne offences both againſt God and thy neighbour.</p>
            <p>Repent and turne, thou knoweſt not if you ſhall liue an houre which is leſſe then a yeare.</p>
            <p>Remember thy mortalitie.</p>
            <p>Remember Chriſts death.</p>
            <p>Remember the deceitfulneſſe of the world.</p>
            <p>Remember the joyes of Heaven.</p>
            <p>Remember the paines of Hell.</p>
            <p>Flie vyce, inquyre for peace, and follow after it, without the which, none can pleaſe God.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The mooveable Feasts.</head>
               <p>EVerie mooveable Feaſt is when each neighbour dynes and ſuppes with others in their houſes,</p>
               <gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
                  <desc>〈1… pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:23893:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 60 -->
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ lines">
                        <desc>〈1… lines〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>THis double heart which to our view appeare,</l>
                  <l>Intends to practiſe miſchiefe all this yeare</l>
                  <l>One thing to thinke and yet to doe another,</l>
                  <l>For worldly gaine to murther friend or brother:</l>
                  <l>God knowes thy thoughts, and will thy deeds reſent,</l>
                  <l>Hels be thy portion, except thou ſoone repent.</l>
               </lg>
               <epigraph>
                  <q xml:lang="lat">Nimis delicatus es frater, ſi vis gaudere cum mundo, &amp; laetari cum Chriſto,</q>
                  <q>Yee are nyce brother if yee looke to enjoy Christ and the World.</q>
               </epigraph>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The yeare hath foure Quarters.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Of Winter.</head>
                  <p>THis Quarter beginneth at the accuſtomed time, &amp; endeth when the Spring beginneth. This ſeaſon is cold, and moe will reſort to Taverns, and Wine ſellers, to enjoy the juce of the Wine, Beire, and ſpirit of Malt: then to ſeeke ſalt Peter for the reſiſting of the enemie: It may fall out that ſuch as bee hote blooded and young, may aſſay their skill to bee minders in theſe ſellers, but if the toole bee blunt and faile them, their labour will bee nought, and ſuch Powder will giue no fire.</p>
                  <p>This ſeaſon, old men ſhall be vnable of the joynts, and ſhall bee more fit to be in the court of Bacchus,
<pb facs="tcp:23893:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                     <!-- PDF PAGE 60 -->
then Venus: Aries is likelie to governe their heads, ſpecially of ſuch as haue young wiues: Moſt men ſhal marrie wiues to bee their helpers, but their wives ſhall over-rule them, and rather become their hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to lead them to doe what they pleaſe: And hee that wants a good wife may bee monſtrous angrie, and availe himſelfe nothing at all.</p>
                  <p>Young women and ſuch as are of a mid age, ſhall bee deſirous to bee governed by Scorpio, in the court of Sagitarius: For the helpe of all men to make them the more able to pleaſure the wiues: let them eate good meat, and drinke ſtronge drinke: and to intertaine chaſtitie, let the wiues eat barley bread and drinke water.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Of the Spring.</head>
                  <p>THE Spring beginneth when the Muſitian tun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his inſtruments and beginneth to play, and endeth when they are wearie and receaues their wages: This ſeaſon will be windy, ſpecially at the ſounding of bagepipes, whiſtles, and Trumpets.</p>
                  <p>Skippers and mariners will doe well not to procraſtinate their home comming if occaſion ſerue them, but to louſe their ankers, and taikels, and heife their ſailes, otherwiſe it may fall out that if their wiues bee fruſtrat of their company they will</p>
                  <gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
                     <desc>〈1… pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb facs="tcp:23893:4"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 61 -->
                  <gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
                     <desc>〈1… pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <p>contention of the people; they ſhall be counted moſt happie that can eſhew both and liue in peace, and who delytes to doe in the contrare, ſhall bee ſo troubled in their mind, that they ſhall thinke that all things ſeemes to their vntemperat braine, like the noyſe of many waters.<lb/>
                     <q xml:lang="lat">Aquae multae, tribulationes multa,</q>
                     <q>Many waters, many troubles.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>Curtizens, punckes, and panders ſhall abound, and to cover their evill deeds, they ſhall take other names and ſurnames to them, and deny their true names, and ſo imitate the Witchest they that are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed with them are like them, and ſhall be partakers of their puniſhments, they ſhall bring a man to a morſell of bread ſaith Salomon: I thinke they ſhall forſake ſuch trade of life, when Taylors, Webſters, and Millers become leil and ſteales none.</p>
                  <p>Some men for worldly gaine, ſhall not bee aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to know that their wiues doeth make them Cuckolds, and ſhall conſent thereto, but honeſt peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſhall ſay to them, woe bee to you Cuckolds that ever you were borne, your wiues hath made you monſters, and makes you beare Hornes.</p>
                  <p>They ſhall reply,
<q>
                        <l>That is no great matter, what am I the worſe:</l>
                        <l>She makes me live a gentleman, and puts money in my purſe.</l>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <q xml:lang="lat">Omnes leges bonae definitionis, verae penitentiae.</q>
                     <lb/>
In this age young men ſhall become as monſter &amp; capped, &amp; ſhall cover their heads with that which
<pb facs="tcp:23893:4"/>
                     <!-- PDF PAGE 61 -->
men vſed to weare vpon their feet.</p>
                  <p>Sturdie Beggars, and Tiuklers, bands and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, may be as well truſted as the Popes pardons.</p>
                  <p>Papiſts, Ieſiuts, and Maſſe-Prieſts may abound in all vyces, becauſe the Pope will giue them as many pardons for every ſinne as may bee packed in a pare of Muck-creils: <hi>Ille de Creatore deſperat quiru crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turam ſpem ponit,</hi> Hee diſpares of the Creator that puts his truſt in a creature.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Of Harveſt.</head>
                  <p>IT is the beſt Harveſt for theeues, when they cut many purſes, Mutton is in greater requeſt with them then Beefe, becauſe they can ſteale 40. ſheepe out of a fold, before they can ſteale an ox out of a ſtall
<q xml:lang="lat">
                        <l>Mirmidonum, Dolopumve aut duri miles <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>liſſis</l>
                        <l>Temperet a lachrymis.—</l>
                     </q>
                     <q>
                        <l>Who can pitie or po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der thoſe things but with tears</l>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>Witches and Sorcerers ſhall abound this ſeaſon, for gaine many ſhall favour them, theſe Witches by ſpels and charmes, will vſe many cures prejudiciall to Phyſitians, but more prejudicall to their patients who beleeues in them for preve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ting of ſuch wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: Iudges ſhould obey Gods word, not to ſuffer a Witch to liue, and but reſpect of perſons, ſhould try all ſuſpect Witches, and who are found guiltie ſhould be delivered to the executioners to be bound vp to the Kings peace in a Sanct Iohnſtoun ribband, and thereafter to bee purged by the element of fire coales and tarbarels.</p>
                  <gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
                     <desc>〈1… pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:23893:5"/>
                     <!-- PDF PAGE 62 --> 
                     <gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
                        <desc>〈1… pages missing〉</desc>
                     </gap>and to ſaue thy money better in time comming, if thou bee wiſe.</p>
                  <p>If thy horſe want meat in thy default, when thou rydes a journey, his weakneſſe, and ſweatneſſe, and hinderance of thy journey, will put thee in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance to feed him better in time comming or elſe reſolue to goe on thy foote in tyme comming.</p>
                  <p>If the ſeaſon bee cold it will remember thee to put on moe cloaths, provyding thou haue them.</p>
                  <p>Hee that remembers not to bee thy friend in thy juſt adoes, neither for prayer, blood, alyance, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers obligations of loue; giue him gold or ſilver &amp; that will make him remember thee.</p>
                  <p>A man that will not cheriſh his wife, and keepe at home with her but forgets theſe dueties, it may be ſhee can make moyen for her ſelfe, to ſupplie thy neglects, while thou remember to doe theſe things thy ſelfe.</p>
                  <p>Hee or ſhee that lends their cloaths, money, or houſhold ſtuffe to their neighbour, and hath not the like themſelves to put on or vſe, neceſſitie ſhall remember them to ſeeke backe their owne and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily cannot haue it.</p>
                  <p>Let Gods benefits in this life, and the joyes of Heaven in the life to come, make thee repent thee of thy ſinfull life: flee ſinne in time comming, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt the Devill, feare GOD, and keepe his comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements: So ſhall thy life bee happie, thy death more happie, and thy peace in heaven happieſt of all.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:23893:5"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 62 -->
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
